Guide to the Dwight Family Papers
Yale University. Department of Manuscripts and Archives
Dwight family papers
1713-1937
MS 187
Yale University. Department of Manuscripts and Archives
5.5
The papers consist of correspondence, financial records, addresses, sermons, writings, photographs, and other memorabilia of Yale President Timothy Dwight (1752-1817) and his family. Relatives in the Edwards, Hooker, Lyman, Strong, Woodbridge, and Woolsey families are represented. The largest quantity of correspondence documents the family life of John William Dwight, a fertilizer manufacturer. Papers of Timothy Dwight (1752-1817) and Timothy Dwight (1828-1916) concern Yale University. The travels of various family members are highlighted.
Dwight family
Conditions Governing Access
The materials are open for research.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Gifts and purchases, 1932-1989. Gift of Eunice Trowbridge, 2005.
Arrangement
Arranged in two series: I. Correspondence and Papers, 1713-1937. II. Family Papers, 1788-1929.
Scope and Contents
The Dwight Family Papers consist of correspondence, financial records, writings, and other memorabilia of Yale President Timothy Dwight (1752-1817), his ancestors, descendants, and other relations. Relatives in the Edwards, Hooker, Strong, Woodbridge, and Woolsey families are represented. The largest quantity of correspondence documents the family life of John Williams Dwight (President Dwight's grandson), his wife Sophia Dwight Dwight, and children Mary Clarissa, Edward Strong, and Emily Cecilia Dwight. The papers also include courtship letters of Mary Alsop Dwight Patrick and professional papers of President Dwight and his grandson, President Timothy Dwight (1828-1916). Though the papers date from 1713 to 1937, most of the papers were produced in the nineteenth century.
The library received the Dwight Family Papers from numerous donors between the 1940s and 1985, and additional materials have been purchased from other sources. Additional Dwight family material is housed in the Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library. The two and one-half linear feet of papers are arranged in two series: I. Correspondence and Papers, 1713-1937 and II. Family Papers, 1788-1929.
Series I includes letters, financial and legal papers, and memorabilia arranged in chronological order, while Series II consists of other types of material arranged by individual. An index to selected correspondents is included at the end of this register.
Series I begins with legal and financial documents of the Dwight family in eighteenth century Northampton, Massachusetts, including deeds, accounts, and probate records (folder 1). There are also a 1748 account of W. B. Dwight's death and letters for Timothy Dwight (1694-1771) to the Rev. Dr. Thomas Foxcroft describing religious activities in the Northampton area. A 1795 letter invites Timothy Dwight to assume the presidency of Yale College, and several letters in folders 1-3 concern Yale matters. Other letters in these folders focus on family affairs and include exchanges between parents and children and husband and wife.
Folder 3 includes medical advice to Timothy Dwight (1816 Dec. 7) on treating a stricture of the urethra and a copy of the original minutes recorded by Benjamin Silliman at President Dwight's bedside on January 10, 1817, the day before his death. These minutes concern directions for the publication of Dwight's writings. Folder 3 also contains remarks by Dwight on the "comparative value" of his sermons and correspondence of his son Timothy Dwight (1778-1844) concerning the posthumous publication of his father's "System of Divinity". The folder also includes correspondence of Benjamin Dwight, Sereno Dwight, Mary Woolsey Dwight, and Theodore Dwight.
The majority of the correspondence in folders 4 and 5 relates to the courtship of Mary Alsop Dwight by Matthew A. Patrick, a career army officer serving in 1832 in South Carolina. His letters include comments on the nullification crisis, which delayed his wedding furlough. A few letters from Mary Alsop (Dwight) Patrick to her father Theodore Dwight describe her life as an officer's wife. Folder 5 also contains correspondence of Theodore Dwight, Jr., concerning the publication of his textbooks, and of Timothy Dwight's (1752-1817) heirs, concerning their claim for a Revolutionary War veteran's pension.
Correspondence between John W. Dwight and his future wife Sophia Dwight of Clinton, New York, begins in folder 5. There are numerous letters to "Sophy" in folders 6 and 7, and folders 8-12 are almost exclusively concerned with this branch of the Dwight family. For a period of a year and a half (1862-1863) John Dwight lived in New Haven, working at a saltpeter business, while his wife and family lived in Clinton, near her family. The almost daily letters between husband and wife concern family finances, weather, the eating habits and behavior of the children (Mary, "Minnie" or "Molly"; Edward, "Ned"; and Emily, "Cecily"), the death of son Louis, John's draft status, and the deteriorating nature of Sophia's health. Following Sophia's death in 1863 there are far fewer letters, but the correspondence through folder 25 is predominantly that of Mary and Edward with their father, now the president of the New Haven Fertilizer Company, uncle Benjamin W. Dwight, and other relations and school friends. Edward graduated from the Yale Medical School in 1886, and several letters concern attempts to establish his medical practice. From folder 17 on there are occasional letters from Timothy Dwight (1828-1916) to non-family members. The majority of these letters are dated after 1888 and concern Yale University business.
Folders 24 and 25 contain additional undated letters of John W. Dwight's family, while folders 26-29 include memorabilia, writings, and financial and legal papers of this same branch of the Dwight family. Folder 28 includes photographs of the Dwight family ancestoral property in Dudley, Massachusetts.
Series II includes papers of Margaret Dwight Bell, Benjamin W. Dwight, Henry Dwight, Timothy Dwight (1752-1817), Susan Edwards Daggett Dwight, and Timothy Dwight (1828-1916). The largest quantity of material relates to Timothy Dwight (1752-1817) and includes sermons and other writings, as well as notes of his sermons and discourses recorded by his son Benjamin W. Dwight, Alexander Phoenix, and an unidentified student in the Yale College seniors' recitation room. Folders 43 and 44 contain Dwight's journals of travels to Cape Cod, Newport, Portsmouth, and Vermont. These were later edited and form a small portion of the published version of Dwight's Travels in New England and New York. (A few additional journals are found in the Humphreys-Marvin-Olmsted Papers, MS 857.) The series includes both printed and manuscript sermons, many of which were delivered at Yale College, and Dwight's poetry.
Benjamin Dwight is represented through biographical writings on his father, some travel observations, and his account of a storm in the Catskills, which he copied and sent to Benjamin Silliman in 1820. Margaret Dwight Bell's papers relate to her 1810 journey from New England to Warren, Ohio. The handwritten copy of her original journal describes the bad roads, inns, and travelling companions she encountered. For Henry Dwight there is a notebook, in German, from studies abroad and a book of hand colored flower engravings. Susan Dwight's papers consist of an autograph album, and for Timothy Dwight (1828-1916) there is a copy of his address at the dedication of Osborn Hall and inscriptions from books presented by him to Battell Chapel. The series concludes with a box containing six pairs of eyeglasses which belonged to Dwight Family relatives.
Biographical / Historical
Timothy Dwight was born on May 14, 1752 in Northampton, Massachusetts. He graduated from Yale College in 1769 (B.A.) and 1772 (M.A.). He served Yale as tutor (1771-1777), Livingston Professor of Divinity (1795-1817), and President (1795-1817). He died on January 11, 1817 in New Haven, Connecticut.
Courtship; Eyeglasses; Families; Voyages and travels; New England -- Description and travel; New Haven (Conn.); Diaries; Sermons; Clergy; College presidents; Educators; Anthony, Elizabeth Dwight, 1831-1870; Anthony, Mary Dwight, 1824-1864; Boudinot, Elias, 1740-1821; Dwight, Agnes Lucy, 1855-; Dwight, Annie Waterman, 1851-; Dwight, Benjamin W. (Benjamin Woodbridge), 1816-1889; Dwight, Benjamin Woolsey, 1780-1850; Dwight, Clarissa Strong, 1783-1855; Dwight, Edward S., 1853-1940; Dwight, Emily Cecilia, 1859-; Dwight, Henry E. (Henry Edwin), 1832-1908; Dwight, John William, 1817-1887; Dwight, Mary Clarissa, 1849-; Dwight, Sophia Dwight, 1818-1863; Dwight, Theodore, 1764-1846; Dwight, Theodore, 1796-1866; Dwight, Timothy, 1694-1771; Dwight, Timothy, 1752-1817; Dwight, Timothy, 1778-1844; Dwight, Timothy, 1811-1842; Dwight, Timothy, 1828-1916; Foxcroft, Thomas, 1697-1769; Lyman, Julia Strong Dwight, 1824-1853; Patrick, Mary Alsop Dwight, 1793-; Patrick, Mathew Alexander, d. 1834; Peck, Julia E.; Strong, Caleb, 1745-1819; Strong, Lewis, 1785-1863; Whitney, Eli, 1765-1825; Dwight family; Edwards family; Hook family; Lyman family; Strong family; Woodbridge family; Woolsey family; Yale University -- Officals and employees; Yale University -- Religion
- Correspondence and Papers, 1713-1937; Series I; 1.25 linear feet (4 boxes)
  Scope and Contents
  This series contains material arranged in chronological order.
  - 1713-1862 (Box 1, Folder 1-11)
  - 1863-1937 February (Box 2, Folder 12-23)
  - undated (Box 3, Folder 24-26)
  - undated (Box 4, Folder 27-28)
  - Financial and legal papers, 1875-1897 (Box 4, Folder 29)
- Family Papers, 1788-1929; Series II; 1.25 linear feet (4 boxes)
  This series contains material arranged alphabetically by the name of the individual. Items for each individual are arranged alphabetically by record type.
  - Bell, Margaret Van Horn Dwight: journal, [ca. 1810] (Box 5, Folder 30)
  - Dwight, Benjamin W.
    - "Biographical Hints & facts respecting the late Revd. Timothy Dwight,", 1817 (Box 5, Folder 31)
    - "Observations on the City of New York,", 1811 (Box 5, Folder 32)
    - "An account of a remarkable storm,", 1819 (Box 5)
  - Dwight, Henry
    - German notebook, undated (Box 5, Folder 33)
    - Flower book, undated (Box 5, Folder 34)
  - Dwight, Timothy (1752-1817)
    - "Discourse … On the character of George Washington, Esq.,", 1800 (Box 5, Folder 35)
    - Notebook, 1798-1801 (Box 5, Folder 36)
    - Poetry, 1792-1817 (Box 6, Folder 37-38)
    - Sermons, Circa 1788-1815 (Box 6, Folder 39-42)
      General
      Folder 40 (1799-1804?) was reported missing in 2006.
    - Travel journals, 1800, 1807, undated (Box 6, Folder 43-44)
    - Writings, undated (Box 7, Folder 45)
    - Notes by others, 1806-1807, 1826, undated (Box 7, Folder 46)
  - Dwight, Susan Edwards Daggett: autograph album, 1825-1836 (Box 7, Folder 47)
  - Dwight, Timothy (1828-1916): address; book inscriptions, 1881-1904 (Box 7, Folder 48)
  - Family coat of arms, undated (Box 7, Folder 49)
  - Family history, [ca. 1929] (Box 7, Folder 50)
    General note
    See also: CF12
  - Eyeglasses, undated (Box 8)
- Additional Material, 1726-1948, undated; Accession 1990-M-033; 3.75 linear feet (9 boxes)
  Addition inventory by Carol King and Randall Law, 1993 Aug
  Received from: Elizabeth Cole Hamill and Katharine Cole Esty, 1989 Dec 20
  - [Anthony], Elizabeth Dwight
    - Correspondence, undated (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Buckingham, William A.
    - Correspondence, 1871 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Cole, Bertha Woolsey Dwight
    - Correspondence, 1881-1905, 1923, 1938, undated (Box 1, Folder 3)
    - Photographs, 1870, 1872, 1891, undated (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Cole, Charles Buckingham
    - Correspondence, 1885, 1887, 1901-1906, 1925, undated (Box 1, Folder 5)
    - Photograph, 1900 (Box 1, Folder 6)
    - Writings
      - "The Legend of the Holy Grail," The Fort Orange Monthly, 1886 September (Box 1, Folder 7)
      - "Twenty Years After": letter, 1907 (Box 1, Folder 8)
      - "Fifty Years After": biography, 1937 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Cole, Charles Wadsworth
    - Bound book of copies of typed letters, 1890s-1900s (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Cole, Charles Woolsey
    - Memorabilia, 1922-1927, 1946, 1948 (Box 1, Folder 11)
    - Photograph, undated (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Cole, Edward H.
    - Stock shares, 1902 (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - Dewey, Lillian (Eliza) Dwight
    - Correspondence
      - 1869 (Box 1, Folder 14)
      - 1878-1880 (Box 1, Folder 15)
    - Photograph, undated (Box 1, Folder 16)
  - Dewey, Richard S.
    - Correspondence, 1874-1879 (Box 1, Folder 17)
    - Photograph, undated (Box 1, Folder 18)
  - Dwight, Benjamin Woodbridge
    - Contracts and documents
      - 1845-1856 (Box 2, Folder 19)
      - 1857-1872 (Box 2, Folder 20)
      - 1881-1896 (Box 2, Folder 21)
    - Copy books, 1825, 1829 (Box 2, Folder 22)
    - Correspondence
      - 1828-1829 (Box 2, Folder 23)
      - 1830-1836 (Box 2, Folder 24)
      - 1837-1839 (Box 2, Folder 25)
      - 1840-1842 (Box 2, Folder 26)
      - 1843-1844 (Box 2, Folder 27)
      - 1845-1847 (Box 2, Folder 28)
      - 1848-1851 (Box 2, Folder 29)
      - 1861-1869 (Box 2, Folder 30)
      - 1872-1878 (Box 2, Folder 31)
      - 1880-1881 (Box 2, Folder 32)
      - 1882 (Box 2, Folder 33)
      - 1883 (Box 2, Folder 34)
      - 1884-1887 (Box 2, Folder 35)
      - undated (Box 2, Folder 36-37)
    - Dewey family genealogy: material
      - 1867-1880 (Box 3, Folder 38)
      - 1882-1883, undated (Box 3, Folder 39)
    - Diary, 1835-1836 (Box 3, Folder 40)
    - Engravings, undated (Box 3, Folder 41)
    - "Ingham University Synopsis,", 1858 (Box 3, Folder 42)
    - Memorials, 1889 (Box 3, Folder 43)
    - Photographs, 1866, undated (Box 3, Folder 44)
    - School catalogs, 1847, 1850, 1861-1863, 1866 (Box 3, Folder 45)
    - Writings
      - Sermons and manuscripts
        - 1830-1836 (Box 3, Folder 46)
        - 1837-1838 (Box 3, Folder 47)
        - Bound book, 1838-1841 (Box 3, Folder 48)
        - 1839 January 20 (Box 4, Folder 49)
        - 1839 April-May (Box 4, Folder 50)
        - 1840-1841 (Box 4, Folder 51)
        - 1842, 1845 (Box 4, Folder 52)
        - Bound book, 1870 (Box 4, Folder 53)
        - undated (Box 4, Folder 54-55)
      - The New York Genealogical and Biographical Record
        - "Descendants of Rev. Benjamin Woolsey"
          - 1873 July (Box 4, Folder 56)
          - 1874 April (Box 4, Folder 57)
          - 1874 July (Box 4, Folder 58)
        - "Last Additions to the History of the Woolsey Family,", 1875 January (Box 5, Folder 59)
        - "Notes on the History of the Dewey Family in America,", 1875 July (Box 5, Folder 60)
        - "Further Additions to Dewey Family History,", 1877 July-October (Box 5, Folder 61)
        - "Rogers' Lineage"
          - 1885 January (Box 5, Folder 62)
          - 1885 Apr, October (Box 5, Folder 63)
        - "Traces of the Dwight Family in Early English History,", 1886 January (Box 5, Folder 64)
      - Assorted writings
        Volume also contains "Reminiscences of the Life and Character of Mrs. Sophia Woodbridge Dwight" by Rev. E. Y. Swift
        - A Book of Original Poetry, 1837 (Box 5, Folder 65)
        - "Notes of My Life,", 1842 (Box 5, Folder 66)
        - "Reminiscences of the Life and Character of Benjamin Woolsey Dwight, M.D.,", 1862 (Box 5, Folder 67)
        - "The Doctrine of God's Providence,", 1869 April (Box 5, Folder 68)
        - The Descendants of John Dwight of Dedham, Mass., 1874 (Box 6, Folder 69)
        - "Intercollegiate College Regattas, Hurdle-Races, and Prize Contests," The New Englander, 1876 April (Box 6, Folder 70)
        - "Woman's Right to Public Forms of Usefulness in the Church,", 1877 April (Box 6, Folder 71)
        - "Address Before the Rural Art Association of Clinton N. Y.,", 1881 June 28 (Box 6, Folder 72)
        - "American Genealogies,", undated (Box 6, Folder 73)
        - "Autobiography,", undated (Box 6, Folder 74)
  - Dwight, Benjamin Woolsey
    - Contracts and documents
      - 1812-1830 (Box 7, Folder 75)
      - 1831-1835, 1850, 1858-1859 (Box 7, Folder 76)
    - Correspondence
      - 1804, 1823-1828 (Box 7, Folder 77)
      - 1829-1834 (Box 7, Folder 78)
      - 1835-1836 (Box 7, Folder 79)
      - 1837-1838 (Box 7, Folder 80)
      - 1841-1844 (Box 7, Folder 81)
      - 1845 (Box 7, Folder 82)
      - 1846 (Box 7, Folder 83)
      - 1847 (Box 7, Folder 84)
      - 1848 (Box 7, Folder 85)
      - 1849 February-June (Box 7, Folder 86)
      - 1849 July-1850 (Box 7, Folder 87)
      - undated (Box 7, Folder 88)
    - Writings
      - "A Dissertation On Chronic Debility of the Stomach," Memoirs of the Connecticut Academy of Arts and Sciences, 1811 (Box 8, Folder 89)
      - "Supplementary Observations on Chronic Debility of the Stomach, Book 1,", 1811 March (Box 8, Folder 90)
  - Dwight, Charlotte Sophia Parish
    - Contracts and documents, 1891 (Box 8, Folder 91)
    - Correspondence
      - 1869, 1873, 1880 June-August (Box 8, Folder 92)
      - 1880 September-October (Box 8, Folder 93)
      - 1885-1898, undated (Box 8, Folder 94)
    - Photographs, 1846, 1876, undated (Box 8, Folder 95)
  - Dwight, Clarissa Strong
    - Correspondence, 1807 (Box 8, Folder 96)
  - Dwight, Edmund
    - Contracts and documents, 1817 (Box 8, Folder 97)
  - Dwight, Edward F.
    - Correspondence and contract, 1900 (Box 8, Folder 98)
  - Dwight, Edward S.
    - Correspondence, 1877-1880, undated (Box 8, Folder 99)
  - Dwight, Emily C.
    - Correspondence, 1877-1881 (Box 8, Folder 100)
  - Dwight, Francis Edwin
    - Correspondence
      - 1883-1884 November (Box 8, Folder 101)
      - 1884 Dec, undated (Box 8, Folder 102)
    - Photographs, 1863-1871, 1878/1879, 1885 (Box 8, Folder 103)
  - Dwight, John M.
    - Correspondence, contracts, documents, 1825, 1854-1863 (Box 8, Folder 104)
  - Dwight, Mary
    - Correspondence, 1848-1849, 1889, undated (Box 8, Folder 105)
  - Dwight, Mary (Molly) Bond Olmstead
    - Correspondence, 1847, 1850, 1899, undated (Box 8, Folder 106)
    - Photograph, undated (Box 8, Folder 107)
  - Dwight, Mary Woolsey
    Most of the correspondence is addressed to Benjamin W. and Timothy Dwight, sons of Mary Dwight.
    - Contracts and documents pertaining to the execution of Mary Dwight's will, 1844-1846 (Box 8, Folder 108)
    - Correspondence, 1831, 1833, 1841, 1844 (Box 8, Folder 109)
  - Dwight, Minnie C.
    - Correspondence, 1872-1885, undated (Box 8, Folder 110)
  - Dwight, Sophia
    - Correspondence and will, 1835, 1843, 1880 (Folder 9, Folder 111)
    - Photograph, undated (Folder 9, Folder 112)
  - Dwight, Sophia Edwards
    - Correspondence, 1884, 1902-1903, undated (Folder 9, Folder 113)
    - Photograph, undated (Folder 9, Folder 114)
  - Dwight, Sophia Woodbridge Strong
    - Contracts and documents, 1822-1832 (Folder 9, Folder 115)
    - Correspondence, 1814-1817, 1825-1837, 1851, undated (Folder 9, Folder 116)
    - Photograph, undated (Folder 9, Folder 117)
  - Dwight, Theodore William
    - Correspondence, contract, clipping, 1837, 1844-1862, 1872, 1884-1892, undated (Folder 9, Folder 118)
    - "The Hamiltonian,", 1879 (Folder 9, Folder 119)
    - "The Dwight Tribute,", 1891 (Folder 9, Folder 120)
    - "Funeral of Hon. Theodore W. Dwight," The Clinton Courier, 1892 July 6 (Folder 9, Folder 121)
    - In Memoriam, Theodore William Dwight, 1892 (Folder 9, Folder 122)
    - Photograph, undated (Folder 9, Folder 123)
  - Dwight, Timothy (b. 1811)
    - Correspondence, 1874 (Folder 9, Folder 124)
  - Dwight, Wealthy Jane Dewey
    - Correspondence, 1847, 1859, undated (Folder 9, Folder 125)
  - Hopkins, Mary Delia
    - Memorial, 1937 (Folder 9, Folder 126)
  - Jana, Joseph
    - Correspondence, [1720] (Folder 9, Folder 127)
  - Ripley, Joshua, Jr.
    - Deed, 1726 (Folder 9, Folder 128)
  - Williams, Othniel Samuel
    - Deed, 1857 (Folder 9, Folder 129)
  - Woodbridge, Jahleel
    - Will, undated (Folder 9, Folder 130)
  - Dwight family Engravings, 1846, undated (Folder 9, Folder 131)
  - Dwight family Photographs
    - 1867/1868, 1869, undated (Folder 9, Folder 132)
    - 1920, undated (Folder 9, Folder 133)
  - Other papers
    - The New York Genealogical and Biographical Record, 1887 July (Folder 9, Folder 134)
    - A Genealogical Register of the Descendants in the Male Line of Robert Day, by George E. Day, 1848 (Folder 9, Folder 135)
    - Clippings, 1816, 1938 (Folder 9, Folder 136)
    - Contracts and documents, 1770, 1864, 1886, 1887 (Folder 9, Folder 137)
    - Correspondence, 1841, 1878, 1893, 1910, 1912, undated (Folder 9, Folder 138)
    - Miscellaneous, 1840, 1887-1888, undated (Folder 9, Folder 139)
  - Oversize (Folder 9)
  - Timothy Dwight family tree (photostat) (Folder 10)
  - The American Boy. October, 1906 (Folder 10)
  - Once A Week: an Illustrated Weekly Newspaper (Folder 10)
  - Vol. V, No. 2, 1890 Apr 29 (Folder 10)